﻿♪ [Music] ♪
$$ Year 6 of the AIDS epidemic. $$
$$ Greenwich Village, New York City.
The epicenter. $$
$$ With no drugs to treat the disease,
AIDS is nearly 100% fatal. $$
$$ Panic drives a backlash
of blame and anti-gay violence. $$
$$ Even hospitals routinely turn away the dying. $$
$$ Fighting for their lives,
patients and their advocates $$
$$ take matters into their own hands. $$
- Welcome to ACT UP. We are
the AIDS Coalition
- [together] to unleash power.
A diverse, non-partisan group
and individuals united in anger
and committed to direct action
-[together] to end the AIDS crisis.
- In less than 12 hours from now,
we are gonna be taking over City Hall.
[Applause]
[Crowd chanting]
- [Ed Koch] Yes.
- *[male reporter] Mr. Mayor, in campaigning
for the lesbian and gay vote,*
in an election year, a bit of
historical context is necessary
in dealing with the AIDS crisis
in New York City.
It wasn't until 1983 that you met
with people to deal with
the AIDS crisis.
How do you respond to these questions?
- [Ed] That it's a falsehood.
- Please, anybody who's
thinking about being arrested,
*fill out a support sheet, make sure
your support person knows who you are*
and what group you're in.
Yeah?
- Um, if we end up in The Tombs,
is there like a queer tank there
and would you recommend that we
ask to be there?
- There is a homo tank
and I've been there
and it's better than the straight tank,
let me tell you.
- [Ed] Who else? Yes?
- [reporter] In the past, you've described ACT UP
as fascist yet in the press release,
you called them concerned citizen.
*I was wondering what changed your mind?*
- [Ed] I don't think that you can't use both.
Fascist can be concerned citizens.
And I don't believe they are fascist.
I think they have used the fascist tactic.
- Let us celebrate together
tonight, the end of the last day
on which Ed Koch can tell himself
that the communities which are
being decimated by this epidemic
are so weak and so divided
among themselves
that he can keep serving us
this kind of bullshit.
[laughter]
Tomorrow morning, he will begin
to learn the truth.
[applause]
- [Female voice] ACT UP, stand tall
tomorrow morning at city hall.
- [Crowd] ACT UP, stand tall
ACT UP, stand tall,
tomorrow morning at city hall.
ACT UP, stand tall...
♪ [Music] ♪
$$ City Hall $$
*- [male reporter] We're talking to Jim Eigo*
*for the Treatment Issues Committee
of ACT UP.*
Jim, what specific treatment issues are pretty
important in this demonstration this week?
*- [Jim Eigo] The municipal hospitals
are totally falling apart.*
*More than half the people
who get diagnosed with AIDS today*
*get diagnosed in the emergency rooms
of our city.*
You're going to find yourself
waiting four days
in an emergency room before
you get a bed.
- I'm pretty scared about being
HIV positive.
I don't have much choice in the matter.
- I just love all these people
and I think that what we're
doing is really right.
And -- I mean, listen to this
and look at our people,
it's just really wonderful
and it's worth putting
*ourselves on the line. *
- *[Ann Northrop] There is
no accurate diagnosis.*
*There are incentives
in the city hospitals*
*not to diagnose people with AIDS,*
and therefore people don't get treated.
We are angry at the way this city
has handled this crisis
and we demand that Ed Koch
exert leadership
and declare a state of emergency.
[Applause]
*- [Peter] Go on the street now or wait,
those are the options.*
One. He says go.
*-Two, now.*
-He says now, three.
Don?
*Go now--*
*-[Reporter] I'm standing here
with Larry Kramer*
*What is ACT UP trying to say today
to Ed Koch?*
-We're sending a message
to public officials,
to closeted public officials
that we won't be shot down anymore
and obviously all the AIDS issues.
*-I would love to see, like,
more cameras or something *
you know, for our own protection.
*-[male voice] and everyone here has concerns--*
*-[Larry] People die everyday.
Friends get sick everyday.*
*I don't--it's like being in the trenches.*
*There's such anger in the community
and that it's coalescing in a way *
that has never been done before.
- Okay, which way do we face girlfriends?
This way or that way?
[crowd talking]
[cars honking]
[crowd cheering and rallying]
[together] HEALTHCARE IS A RIGHT.
HEALTHCARE IS A RIGHT.
- [police officer talking]
[crowd shouting]
♪ [music] ♪
$ How To Survive A Plague. $
- I guess, I'm feeling pretty hopeless
at the moment.
I think that the biggest question that
I'm facing now is how to remain hopeful
in the face of increasing loss.
- *[David Barr] I don't know,
maybe it sounds really corny *
but I--
as difficult as the time is for us,
I like being alive.
And I love my friends and I love my family.
*I love people around me.*
- This, I'm gonna die from this.
This isn't gonna be cured for
years and years and years and years.
*- Doctor's office?*
- [speaking in the phone] Hi, it's Peter Staley.
It's like living in a war.
All around me,
friends are dropping dead.
And you're scared for your own life
all at the same time.
*I was diagnosed with AIDS-related complex*
*while I was working as a bond trader
on Wall Street.*
*I had night sweats.*
*I began to get dry, patchy, scaly,
itchy skin on my face. *
*And I would get sick constantly.*
*Colds would lay me up for weeks.*
I started to look around in desperation
for ways that I could find treatments
to help save my life.
And there was nothing coming out of our
government's efforts, I quickly realized.
*Everything I read said I had about
two years to live, at most. *
[Crowd shouting]
$ ACT UPS first protest
March 24, 1987 $
*-[male voice] WHAT DO WE WANT?*
*-[crowd answering] A CURE!*
*-[male voice] WHEN DO WE WANT IT?*
*-[crowd answering] NOW!*
*-[Peter] I was on my way to work and
I got handed a flier about ACT UP and AIDS.*
*My mentor says, "If you ask me,
I think they all deserve to die" *
*"because they took it up their butt."*
*I was deeply closeted and I had to
just stew about it for the rest of the day.*
*I got myself to the very next ACT UP meeting.*
*They could just tap into that
immediate anger and get stuff done.*
*-[female voice] We need to get approval
on this...*
*This is a non-violent
and quiet kiss-in.*
We will not leave until
the administrator meets with us
and tells us that Saint Vincent's
is willing to make a public statement
condemning gay and lesbian violence.
[crowd cheering and applauding]
- All those in favor?
*-All those oppose?*
[car passing]
*-[male voice] They're coming.*
*You see that right there.*
*You've heard of ACT UP,
you've seen our flyers.*
*The kiss-in happens tonight.*
*-[male voice] ACT UP, FIGHT BACK.*
*Take gloves, ACT UP. Woo, woo.*
*-[male voice] I'll deal with the camera.*
*-[female voice] Are your own
security guards ever beat people up here?*
[people chattering]
- Members of the mainstream media
were thrown out as we were
earlier on but Steve and I
came back in and we'll bring you
this exclusive footage inside...
- Don't destroy property,
you're destroying property, okay?
- Actually, you've damaged
some human property last week.
- You will not beat up on faggots
and you will not beat up on lesbians
in hospitals in our own community.
- Two gay women were beaten up,
and when her lover came to respond,
*you know the story. *
*And another story was, two gay guys came,
and one was sick with AIDS. *
*The security guard told him
to get the fuck out of here*
*and called him, "Faggot."*
I think if you're gonna work,
especially in Greenwich Village,
you should have some sensitivity training
because we're not gonna have it.
- I'm willing to meet with three people,
the rest of you leave.
[crowd chattering]
- It's unclear how to play it.
My own instinct would be to say,
"We'd be glad to meet with you
when the meeting is over, we'll leave".
Not to leave before the meeting
takes place.
- Gregg?
- We show the kind of power we can have
by immediate action, by sticking together,
by reaching a consensus together.
We should take the same steps,
we should be cool headed.
- I'm gonna take a straw poll, okay?
*And we agreed to leave the waiting room*
*while he met with
three of our representatives,*
*Gregg, Jerry and Neil
in that public space right there.*
And then we would sit around out here
and wait for the outcome.
- *[Peter] So I said, "Enough of this. This job
is going to kill me." *
So I went on disability and decided
to become a full time AIDS activist.
♪ [music] ♪
*- [Dr. Starrett] In the beginning,
what drugs did we have?*
*We had nothing.*
And the pneumonia could come on like that
and be gone,
and the person is dead.
The skin lesions,
the Kaposi Sarcoma, was--
people would be coming in with it,
with a purple spot.
Everybody was coming in with,
"What is this spot?"
"What is that spot?"
YouI have some guys come on
with K.S. on their face
and they'd been putting makeup
on their face and--
it was--and they were lucky
if it just stayed in their skin,
if it didn’t go into their lungs.
And then if it went into their lungs,
chemo didn't work and then they were gone.
You were grasping at straws for everything
because these are young vibrant people.
And all of the sudden
they're being snatched.
*I think everything has to be put
in perspective. *
$ - We do not know whether this drug
will do the same thing in a human being $
$ it does in test tube for
HIV-infected cells. $
$ And we don’t know how this drug
will respond to people $
$ who are HIV-positive. $
$ - I understand that and
I'm willing to try to find out-- $
$ - I think this is the thing,
it's the only thing I haven’t tried. $
$ I've tried everything else. $
$ - And if you'll just your name to this. $
$ - You'll have stories to tell
in the future $
$ - [male] I'm sure we all will. $
- [male] Okay. Iris Long is life-saving
- *You can't hear in the back,
if you want to, just shout it out, please.*
- [Iris] This is a report of the
American Society of Microbiology,
a conference I went to at the end of May.
- *[male shouting] Quiet!*
- There were many infections talked
about including the AIDS at this conference,
and it was overwhelming to know
how many pathogens, bacteria, fungus,
protozoas, and viruses that are out there
that can really make you very sick.
- *[Larry] One day this woman
just showed up, this housewife. *
*who had been a scientist and still was*
*and said, "You guys don't diddly
about what this is". *
and anybody who wants to learn about
the system, how it works,
how grants were made, how the science
works, how everything works,
how the NIH works,
how the FDA works,
how you can deal with all of this enormous
amount of material, I'll teach you.
- There should be much more funding
than there is for our infectious diseases.
- *Iris was not gay,
but she could not see *
*what was going on around her
and what she knew*
not reaching out to the
affected communities of AIDS.
- *I waited and went up to Iris
afterwards and said, *
"I'm interested in what you were saying.
I'd like to know more."
"I'd like to help."
- And a few people joined her and
that became a bigger and bigger group,
and that became the
*Treatment and Data Committee.*
*T and D. *
- [Garance]...anything else.
There's so many--
- *It was kind of a dorky activity
for a bunch of East Village *
hipsters and artists to sit around,
reading medical journal articles.
- [male talking]
- *We called it Science Club,
like it was Chess Club or something. *
- There aren’t drugs...
- *Individual after individual had
to come to grips with the fact *
*that I will survive the longest,
the most I know about*
*what I'm putting into my body. *
*So they all had to become scientists
to some degree. *
- *...and what I would like
everyone to do *
will be to keep on thinking of ways
to refine these things
to make them more clear to people
that don't necessarily know the issues.
Like, OI, the windows of OI, okay?
So I wrote it here just in shorthand.
*Only 17% of people in their trials
have been taking drugs *
for opportunistic infections or cancers.
- *[Garance] Mark wasn’t like
the big beef cakey guy.*
*He was super smart. Smoked non-stop.*
- *[male] Right away, Mark digested,
as by osmosis, everything. *
*and within a few weeks, he had come up
with a glossary of AIDS treatment terms*
*and we started giving it out in our meeting. *
[people talking]
- And that's by Tom Dwaine regarding--__
[applause]
- This is Bernard Braderman.
who is in danger of being evicted
from his apartment that he shared
with his life partner for many, many years.
His life partner died and the landlord
wants Bernard out of his home
because his name was not on the lease.
- *What's his landlord's address? *
[crowd laughing]
*We'll find it.*
- There are cards here,
the fill outs we'll write to the Governor,
Let's make sure that our voices
are heard in New York City
to save the homes of PWA's
and other nontraditional families.
Thank you very much.
[applause]
- *[Bob] I just wanna say something on
what's just happened? *
I realized we haven’t done anything yet
for him and we haven’t been effective,
and we haven’t been powerful,
but we will be.
It's very inspiring to know
the power of this room
is potentially available to each
and everyone of us.
[applause]
♪ [music] ♪
- What?
How's it?
Is that as good as daddy's or better?
- Mommy yours is better.
- Yey!
- *Would you like daddy to try it?*
Are you ready?
- Yes.
[laughing]
- Dada very good.
- *One, two, three.*
- *[male] I know the sounds ironic
considering it ended in divorce.*
*But I think it is fair to say,*
*it's the only really successful
love affair of my life.*
I came out at age 40.
It was very bad timing to come out
in the middle of an epidemic.
The question is,"What does the
decent society do with people
who hurt themselves because they're human,
who smoked too much, who eat too much,
who drive carelessly,
who don't have safe sex?
I think the answer is that the decent
society does not put people out to pastor
and let them die,
because they'd done a human thing.
♪ [music] ♪
- [reporter] For the first time today,
the government approved prescription sales
of a drug to treat AIDS.
The drug, AZT, is not a cure for the disease,
but it has prolonged the lives
of some AIDS victims.
- *[reporter] It's the only
government-approved AIDS drug in America.*
*But even this most promising drugs,
is the source of frustration and anger.*
*At $10,000 a year cost per patient,
it's prohibitively expensive for most,*
*and not widely available. *
[crowd shouting]
- *[Peter] The AZT is the
most expensive drug in history. *
*They charge $10,000 a year. *
*We need to get a substantial
price reduction out of this company. *
- The incident began at 10:00
this morning,
*when four AIDS activists took over
an office at Burroughs Wellcom, *
*saying they had enough food and water
to stay hold up for a long time. *
*The activists are demanding that
Burroughs Wellcom lower its price of AZT.*
- Burroughs Wellcom is profiting off of our lives.
That's why we did today what we did.
And if they don't see to start listening
to my community--to our community,
the AIDS community,
then we're gonna be back.
♪ [music] ♪
- *[Dr. Starrett] One of the worst, worst things*
*was when people died in the hospital.*
They used to put them in black trash bags.
It was--
It was really awful.
And not every funeral parlor would
take patients, who had died of AIDS.
- But so the least we could
have is sympathy and moral support, you know,
and kindness and support,
and that they deserved in any case.
And even that became denied, you know,
by the authority and rules of organizations
of institutions, it was really horrifying.
- [Newsman] It is the most frightening
medical mystery of our times.
*AIDS victims must deal with the trauma
of being both a patient and a pariah.*
- I hate to use the word gay
in connection with sodomy.
There's nothing gay about these people.
Engaging in incredibly offensive
and revolting conduct that has led
to the proliferation of AIDS.
- There is a feeling among members of any--
of a number of professions
or just the general population,
*that patients with AIDS, many of whom
are homosexual, are a little bit different.*
*I think that that has led
to a little bit *
of a complacency about the approach
towards this disease.
- In the absence of adequate healthcare,
we have learned to become our own clinicians,
*researchers, lobbyist, drug smugglers,
pharmacists.*
*We have our own libraries, newspapers,
drugstores and laboratories. *
- *[Garance] Some of the medications
that were made available were not effective.*
*They were in these categories
that we called, "What-the-hell drugs", *
*which is--there are some evidence
that could be useful. *
*It's unlikely to be harmful. *
What the hell!
- Should I type?
- *Yes, type. *
*Take your time.*
*Where are we?*
- We're at the
People with AIDS Health Group,
The largest underground buyer's club
in the United States.
- *And what do you do here?*
- We help people import drugs
from other countries that aren't approved here.
- Peptide T, albendazole,
oral amphotericin-B,
and the whole variety of things
for your treatment pleasure.
None of which work, by the way.
[laughing] Put that in.
- People with AIDS, what they were mostly
thinking about was,
"Oh, drugs, how do I get it off market?
how do I..."
"Will we ever get a black market
for this drug?"
"I hear, this is good."
It was Iris, who helped us see,
we don’t want a black market.
We wanna make the real market work.
- Try it.
Hi, I'm Mark Harrington
from ACT UP New York.
Recently, a lot of activists who have been
asking, "Why ACT UP is going--"
No. We've got to start over, I've gotta do--
I've gotta do another.
- *You can just start or something. *
- But I won't get that wonderful
cigarette-lighting thing.
- I think the cigarette maybe is not
gonna work at all.
- I shouldn’t use the cigarette at all?
- *No. *
- Really?
- *I don't think so, it's too much. *
- Too much?
Hi, I'm Mark Harrington
from ACT UP New York.
A lot of people have been asking,
"Why are AIDS activists going to the FDA?"
*First of all, you have to understand
that the FDA is one of the *
*many federal aides bureaucracies,
which we're angry with *
*for not doing enough on the fight
against the AIDS. *
*Half the people who take AZT
can't take it because of side effects. *
*Therefore, the FDA has to take a more
activists' stance in the experimental process.*
And only the FDA has the power
under existing laws and regulations
to release the drugs
that we want released now.
How's that?
- Amazing.
[crowd shouting together]
*AZT IS NOT ENOUGH!*
*GIVE US ALL THE OTHER STUFF
AZT IS NOT ENOUGH!*
- *[Vito] It takes nine months
to test this drug in Europe, in Belgium,*
*in France, in Germany, in England.
We are not asking the FDA to release *
*dangerous drugs without safety or efficacy.*
*We are simply asking the FDA to do it quicker.*
[crowd shouting]
- Dextran sulfate for sale.
"There's no dextran here, you can't get in inside."
- ...the FDA, but we're selling it anyway.
- Three dollars for dextran sulfate. Three dollars!
[crowd chanting]]
Release the drugs now! Release the drugs now!
[crowd chanting]
Get to work! Get to work!
[crowd chanting] Guilty! Guilty! Guilty!
[crowd chanting] Seize control!
[crowd chanting] ACT UP! FIGHT BACK!
FIGHT AIDS!
♪ [music] ♪
- *[male] We don't know where
they're taking us. *
We're here because this government has
the resources to deal with the AIDS epidemic
and they won't do it unless we force them.
- *[newsman] I do have reports live from Rockville
*
where the massive protest is wrapping up, Roger.
- *[Roger] Well Jim, it's being billed
as one of Montgomery County's *
*biggest demonstrations in recent
history and it went off smoothly. *
*One hundred eighty-five arrested,
as coalition of gay groups came to Rockville*
*to shut down the FDA. *
- *[TV announcer] Tonight, from Washington,*
Crossfire: Against All Odds.
*On the left, Tom Braden.
On the right, Pat Buchanan.*
*In the Crossfire, Peter Staley of the
New York AIDS Coalition to unleash power.*
- [Tom] Peter Staley, you have the
AIDS virus and I am sorry.
but don't you think that the
Federal Drug Administration
has a responsibility not to let people,
such as you, have quack
that could cause even more harm
than you already have?
- The problem is, is that
the FDA is using the same process to test
a nasal spray at it is to test AIDS drugs,
and it's a seven to ten-year process.
- You have the FDA giving you a drug.
So far, you've got AZT. Why would--
- Which I can't take because it's far too toxic.
- But there--
- Remember, over half the people that
have HIV can't take it.
- Okay. But the FDA says there
is nothing else that is worth anything.
- Mr. Staley, this is gonna astonish you,
but I agree with you a hundred percent.
I think if someone's got AIDS and someone
wants to take a drug, it's their life,
and if it gives them hope,
you ought to be able to take it.
What I wanna ask you is whether you know
of anything that you think might be
some kind of miraculous cure that you think
they're sitting on at FDA?
- There are over 140 drugs out there that
the FDA has identified as possibilities,
and are in some stage are
being looked up right now.
- Why are they holding back--
- Among that 140, there's gotta be one
or combination thereof that can slow down
this virus or halt it in its tracks.
- You're just simply carrying the virus,
is that correct?
- I have a few very minor symptoms
and my immune system is virtually shot.
- What would you like to take that you--
- I would like to be able
- to take Dextran Sulfate legally,
I'm taking it on the underground right now.
*- How would that hurt you?*
-Well, why not, Mr. Braden?
- [Tom] Because--for I don't know anything
about Dextran Sulfate, and neither do you--
- Well, I'll tell you this,
it's an over-the-counter drug in Japan
and has been for 20 years, over-the-counter.
- *[Pat] Over-the-counter in Japan? *
- Yes.
- [Tom] But if the FDA says--
- *[Pat] Mr. Staley--*
- I'm only asking that they be released after--
after there's a minimal amount of efficacy,
not a 100% test.
- *[Pat] --get something here. *
You've got the pink triangle on your shirt,
I gather that means you're a homosexual.
- Yes.
- *Looking in the camera,*
what would you tell some kids,
say, you had a younger brother,
twenty-one years old,
who also might have homosexual tendencies,
what would you tell him if you want him
to live a long life?
- Use a condom, and also to use
a lubricant, by the way,
that has the medicine--
- [Pat] And actually this is *Russian roulette.*
- It is not Russian roulette.
It is Russian roulette to not give people
this information when human nature
dictates that they're gonna go out there
and they're gonna have sex anywhere.
- You mean celibacy is impossible?
- It's not just gonna work.
People aren’t gonna do it
and lots of people are gonna die.
Now, would you rather have a lot of people
cheating under the celibacy
with thousands of people dying
or would you rather save those lives?
and let them have sex.
- Well, I think that--well.
Thank you very much, Peter Staley,
thanks for being in our studio,
Mr. Braden and I will be back in a minute.
♪ [music] ♪
- *[male voice] One of the things we wanted
was a drug that you gave to people*
*who had cytomegalovirus and advanced AIDS.*
*because people who had both,
tended to go blind.*
*It was called* DHPG.
♪ [music] ♪
- *In a way somewhat the AZT,
it was highly toxic,*
*but it was known to be effective,
because 6000 people*
*had already used the drug
but never in a clinical trial.*
[crowd shouting]
- We're with Jim Eigo from ACT UP,
and there's a major protest going on
here in Bethesda over the drug DHPG.
Tell us what's happening.
- Well, this is the second meeting
of the Bush Commission
for reviewing procedures for approving
AIDS and cancer drugs,
and we thought since the non-approval
of DHPG is such a perfect example
of how regulation has gone wrong,
we bring at home to the commission itself
by showing up here in force
and that's what we've done.
- Okay. Also inside at the hearing itself,
*and I understand there's going to be an action*
*in just a little while
when Ellen Cooper speaks. *
- *I guess so.*
- [crowd talking together]
*What about DHPG?*
- Without the objective data,
we feel that we would indeed
be on treacherous grounds
in defending that decisions. And in fact,
we'd be wide open to the charge
of arbitrary decision making.
Although, we certainly
wouldn’t be accused of being inflexible.
- *[male] You did it with the AZT --
- [male 2] Exactly.*
[crowd shouting]
- I mean, I'd like to say that the difference
in the data between AZT and DHPG,
it is the difference between night and day--
[crowd talking together]
- *[male] Two people died since this meeting started*
*and four more are gonna die before it's over.*
- *[male 2] Who represents patients on this panel?*
- [Dr. Cooper] There is a person with cholera
on this panel.
- FDA re-looks at the DHPG data,
and suddenly all agrees with ACT UP.
- *[male] Ready for vote?
All in favor, raise your hand.*
- *[male voice] One, two...*
- *[male] Oh, that's over.*
[applause and crowd cheering]
- *It was really an amazing encounter*
*but it sort of felt like reaching the Wizard of Oz.*
Like, you got to the center of the whole system
and there's just this schmuck behind the curtain.
*There was no guiding agenda.
There was no leadership.*
*There was no global strategy
for how to deal with AIDS in the U.S.*
*And so when the bus back from Bethesda,
we decided to write a treatment agenda*
*because nobody was dealing with
the entire map of AIDS,*
*the entire constellation of
opportunistic infections,*
*the gaps in research,
the under-represented populations,*
the fact that the diseases and the drugs
might be different in those populations.
How would they be able to find out?
They weren’t even being studied.
[crowd shouting]
♪ [music] ♪
- *Bye Rob!
Bye Bobby!*
♪ [music] ♪
- [crowd shouting] GAY CRISIS KNOWS
NO BOARDERS!
- *[Peter] I'd just like to say that
the reasons I can't get any of these drugs*
*is because for nine years now,*
*the leadership in this country has failed
to come up with a plan of action.*
They failed to come up with a plan
of research, a national research agenda.
People with AIDS and their advocates have
finally done this for them.
This is it.
This is the plan we're presenting.
We need our government to read this plan,
and we need them to work with us.
If they wanna change it a little,
we'll talk to them.
But I want them to adopt it.
I want them to get started on it.
I want them to save our lives.
Thank you.
- I snuck around and grabbed one
of those copies and it was very interesting.
- We believe that the United States
has a global responsibility
to create and develop effective treatments
not only for HIV infection itself,
but for all of the opportunistic infections,
which actually caused suffering and death
to the people living with AIDS.
- [Iris] This is not a new agenda,
and it is not an agenda of only ACT UP.
Scientists agree with this.
Why can't we have it?
- Researchers and regulators are going to
have to come up
with a parallel release program
that will get drugs to the people who need it,
before the five years down the pipe
where they may be approved by the FDA.
- *[Susan] I was scribbling madly*
*in this copy
of their AIDS treatment research agenda.*
I would go back and forth between saying,
"No, no! They don't understand!"
To saying, "Whoa! You mean this isn't
the way we're doing trials?"
"You mean, people aren’t allowed to do
this or that?"
But I have to tell you that I was still not ready
to sort of go up to them and try and engage.
*I brought this copy back and I distributed it
to a small group of statisticians*
*that was meeting regularly
to talk about trial design issues.*
The people sitting around that table
got as excited as I did.
This had clearly been written by people
who were very knowledgeable,
very intelligent and really wanted to do
the trials the best possible way.
They were not against trials.
They wanted to get the right answers,
but they wanted what they called,
"Humane trials".
- It all came together in Montreal,
but what was new for ACT UP?
We went to a drug company.
- *[reporter] There is renewed hope
for people infected with AIDS.*
*A new experimental drug, DDI,
will be distributed on a limited basis*
*for free this fall by its developer,
the giant Bristol-Myers Company.*
*This marks the first time an anti-AIDS
drug will be available even before*
*safety testing is finished.*
*Full AZT treatment is too much
for patient, Peter Staley.*
*For nine months, he has been limited
to a quarter dose of the drug. *
*And wants DDI as soon as possible.*
- Do you need DDI to live, do you think?
- Yes. I need DDI and I probably need
some other antivirals beyond that.
- *[Larry] It is historic,
it is because the AIDS activist community*
has obtained this drug.
It is not the government.
No one has given it to us,
we have fought for it.
And for the first time,
we have won.
- *[Mark] So, by '89, less than a year
after our FDA demo,*
*they had approved a drug to prevent
blindness in people with AIDS.*
*and we got an expanded access to DDI,
and that was a very powerful feeling.*
*We felt like we were taking direct action*
*and we were helping make
people's lives better.*
*I wasn’t sure that AZT or DDI
were all that great. *
*But we were beginning to get letters
from people that said, *
*"Thank you for saving my eyesight.
Thank you ACT UP for getting me access*
*to DDI and helping to save my life".*
- [Emilio] At Merck, HIV was an important
scientific target.
HIV of course is a virus.
In order for the virus to infect
an uninfected cell,
it needs to construct itself
in a particular way.
*First, the viral RNA needs
to transform itself into a DNA copy,*
*in order to knit itself into
the nuclear DNA of the newly infected cell.*
*This occurs via process called,*
reversed transcription.
*AZT and DDI were both
originally developed to try to inhibit*
*that process of establishing infection.*
*A number of other researchers
began to focus on another portion*
*of the viral life cycle,
after the cell is already infected.*
One of the steps that it takes is that
it makes a viral protein.
It has to snip that viral protein
in very specific places.
*The resulting pieces self-assemble
to make the viral particle.*
*And what does the snipping
and what in fact controls the snipping,*
*is a viral protein called,
the protease.*
*If you genetically modified the viral protease,
so that it can no longer snip--*
*The virus no longer has the ability
to make those component pieces*
*that it need to make in order
to self-assemble*
*and make an infectious viral particle.*
- [Joseph] We solved the structure
of HIV protease
in 1989, and published it pretty quickly.
I think we saw the structure and within
a few weeks, it was in the literature.
- And then the question became,
"Alright, can we prove it?
Can we prove it that that is in fact the case?
And most importantly, can we prove that
if you inhibit that protease,
if you knock out its activity,
that the virus can no longer replicate,
and therefore make new progeny
viral particles that would
then go on and establish
a cycle of infection?
- *[reporter] AIDS is now the leading
cause of death for men under 44*
*in New York and the half-dozen
other cities*
*surpassing homicide
and all other diseases.*
*Yet, Roman Catholic Bishops
are meeting this week*
*to publicly oppose the use of condoms
as morally unacceptable. *
*This puts them in direct opposition
to U.S. Public Health Policy.*
♪ [music] ♪
- *The new church position condemns
not only the immorality of condoms,*
*but their effectiveness as well. *
*The draft under consideration
in Baltimore this week says, *
*it is, "A virtual certainty that reliance on
condoms will result*
*in transmission of AIDS."*
*Of the bishops' proposed new policy,*
*New York City Health Commissioner,
Stephen Joseph says,*
- *[Stephen Joseph] This would be a
public health disaster.*
It would undoubtedly lead to
more transmission particularly
in high-risk areas of the city.
More disease and more death.
- *[reporter] Catholic conservatives say,
"Not just physical death,"*
*but spiritual death is an issues here."*
*As New York City's archbishop,
John Cardinal O'Connor put it,*
- The use of prophylactics
is immoral in a pluralistic society
or any other society.
♪ [music] ♪
- Except, of course, we have Ann Northrop,
giving her sound-bite technique.
[crowd applauding and cheering]
- We want everybody
to join us, to support us,
*to destroy the power of the Catholic Church.
To make our side the strong one.*
*And to do that, we must put out
the message that we are the ones*
who are fighting for people's lives
and they are the murderers.
*Don't be afraid of the media,
you're talking through them to the public.*
We are trying to arouse, to anger
and action and hone it down to, yes,
a three-second bite, a five-second bite.
Just a phrase that will have an impact,
that will say something specific,
and it will be understandable.
So...
[crowd laughing]
I don't have a phrase worked out and--
[laughing]
So, you're gonna have to create your own.
So this is empowerment.
[crowd laughing]
♪ [music] ♪
- This is Jesus Christ, I'm front of
St. Patrick's Cathedral on Sunday.
We're here reporting on
a major AIDS activist
and abortion rights activist demonstration,
which will be taking place here all morning.
Inside, Cardinal O'Connor
is freely spreading his lies and rumors
about the position of lesbians and gays.
We're here to say,
"We wanna go to heaven too."
$$ - *Recent publicity indicates
a possibility of protest activities* $$
$$ *occurring within the Cathedral. $$*
$$ *We wish to remind all visitor
to respect the prayerful atmosphere* $$
$$ *at the Cathedral today.* $$
- J.C. here with the Fire and Brimstone
network.
And we would like to ask you
a little bit about this
large vision that you visited upon us.
- Well, we decided to rename
the cardinal, he's now Cardinal O'Condom.
This is our message to him
that condoms are safe, it's no fib.
$$ - *And he then told them what was
going to happen, it did happen.* $$
$$ *[crowd shouting] Why are you murdering us? * $$
$$ *Stop the madness!!!* $$
$$ - [priest] If everyone here could stand and pray… $$
$$ *Our Father-- $$*
$$ - *Prayers won't save the
1 to 1.5 million people* $$
$$ infected by human immunodeficiency virus! $$
[whistle blowing]
- Stop killing us! Stop killing us!
We're not gonna take it anymore!
You're killing us!
Stop it! Stop it! Stop it! Stop it!
[crowd shouting together]
*Stop it! Stop it! Stop it!*
- How many more have to die?
How many more have to die?
[crowd making noise]
- *[Cardinal O'Conner] Those protesting
believe that the protest will result *
*in some change of environments
and change of attitudes perhaps.*
The church will be teaching that
homosexual activity is sinful
until the end of time.
That won't change.
♪ [music] ♪
- *This is July 22nd, 1989.*
- *[female voice] Sara, what do you think
about your dad being 44?*
- Good.
[people laughing]
- *[Bob] I guess, thank you for your support.*
One, two, three!
- Yehey! Yehey!
- A lot of smoke.
- *Oh, boy!*
- *[Bob] I wish those candles will stop smoking,
it's bad for their health.*
- *[female voice] That's right.*
*Okay, Robert Resty,
*
*do you have any rebuttal before
you jump off the edge of the porch?*
- I have no interest in jumping off
the edge of the porch .
I will jump up and down.
I think 44 is a very fine age.
It has a nice symmetry to it.
It has nice feeling to it.
It's better than 22
and possibly better than 88, we'll see.
[woman laughing]
- Here's how we planned this.
What we want to do is
run this light in Treatment and Data meeting.
A number of times we've had people come
to the Treatment and Data meeting,
and speak on certain issues.
*We try to get in-depth.*
*We try to nail issues down.
This isn't a free-for-all. *
Let's call it a working confrontation.
*So, where do we start? *
*This is Dr. Anthony Fauci.
Rob, you're allowed to speak.*
- *[Bob] I may be wrong, Dr. Fauci,*
*but it's my understanding that
thousands of people died from pneumonia*
*because there was no priority
within the government,*
*or within the medical system as a whole,*
*to push the known preventive treatments
for a long time.*
*Now, those thousands of people are dead.*
*It would seem to me that someone*
who was within the government,
while that took place as you work,
must have wrung your conscience
of these deaths.
- That is a tough one.
- No, it really is.
It's inexcusable that
an academic priority should ever,
ever come before the health of the people
that you're working with.
*There's no questions about that,
but the reality of the situation is,*
there was a great reluctance
among the community of everything
from the scientists to the congress
saying that
what we should be doing
is not telling investigators what to do
but we should allow them to do
what they feel is the most important.
Now, that sounds awful
when you're putting into the context
of what we're talking about here.
But the whole world isn't in this room.
[crowd making noise]
- *[Reporter] AIDS activists storm
the government's premier*
*disease research center.*
*The National Institutes of Health,
where an AIDS cure might be found.*
*It is where therapies are
being tested in clinical trials. *
- [crowd shouting] No more secret meetings!
- *Demonstrators blocked access
to buildings.*
*Scientists and administrators reporting
to work stood around, looking confused.*
*Activists charge the
Bush administration with foot dragging *
*on AIDS research.*
*It's not the amount of
Federal money allocated to it,*
*it's so much as how
research priorities are defined.*
- We need new drugs to people alive.
But the NIH is only testing old the drugs.
Drugs that we already have.
- *Can you tell us what you're doing?*
- Hi! I'm Jimmy Johnson,
and I'm in a clinical trial here.
And right now, I'm observing and
participating in the ACT UP demonstration.
- *[female reporter] Why?
Why do you support this action?*
- Because we need far more AIDS research.
And we're just beginning.
- *[female reporter] What trial are you in? *
- *I'm in Interleukin 2/AZT Combinations
Drug Study.*
- *[female reporter] Are there any
women in your trial?*
- No. There aren’t any women at all.
- *[female reporter] People of color?*
- No, there are not.
- *[female reporter] Why do you think that is? *
- *[Jimmy] It's just the beginning
of the problem.*
- Garance] Three major things that control
NIH Research,
stupidity, incompetence, and greed.
Those are the three major driving force behind
what's going on here,
and why there are no treatments
out there for people living
with this disease.
[crowd shouting]
- *[female supporter] We're not going down that way. *
*Dr. Anthony Fauci is coinciding
with research priorities*
*for the National Institute of Allergies
and Infectious diseases.*
*We're down here because we think
we should be deciding the research priorities,*
because these are the people
who know what's going on,
because they're dealing with it everyday.
[crowd making noise]
- [crowd shouting]
*The whole world is watching! *
[crowd making noise]
[THUMP!]
- If anything the mood after the NIH
was even bleaker than the mood before.
Because we had no indication that they
were gonna change or respond to our demands.
And we had in fact had a meeting with them
in Bethesda, after the NIH action.
That indicated that there was
total resistance to putting people
from the community on the research committees,
to let in the ACT UP observers attend the meetings,
and to open up the meetings
so that they weren't secret anymore.
So why should Science
be shrowded in secrecy?
It's supposed to be based on
a free exchange of ideas.
And so, it was very important
to stage in San Francisco,
before again the global community of
scientist and people working on AIDS,
why we had been at the NIH.
Why the U.S. systems wasn’t working out.
And to reach the people directly that we had
reached symbolically through the NIH action.
- *[newsman] About a hundred protesters
have already been arrested *
at the international AIDS conference
that began today in San Francisco.
Hundreds more are angrily
protesting a government policy
they say, "Neglects research
and ostracizes victims."
- *[David] Why don't do informational
slide first? *
United States has the most discriminatory
immigration policies regarding HIV.
- I could say, as a way to bridge the rift
between the scientific community,
all of you and the activists,
we'd like you to join in some activism.
*[Peter] And I've always been painfully aware*
*that in order for me to beat this virus and live, *
*I will need a great deal of help
from all of you. *
Can we all, before it's too late,
begin to understand each other.
Will we realize that we share
similar motivations.
During the upcoming days,
ACT UP New York will be handing out
our AIDS treatment agenda,
which includes a list of 99 drugs
that we believe could be ready
for small phase 1 studies,
*this year or next.*
However, from your side,
we are being constantly told to butt out.
On my side, the level of anger
and frustration is reaching such a point
that attitudes claiming that all of you are
uncaring and in it for greed
*are now widespread.*
While at times we may offend you,
remember as well that like you,
ACT UP has succeeded in prolonging
the lives of thousands of people
living with HIV disease.
[audience applauding and cheering]
I would like to be joined
in front of the stage
by my fellow AIDS activists.
If you all come up?
*At this moment, there are others just like us,*
*who are trying to get into this conference,*
but are being barred by the
billy clubs of San Francisco Police.
And there are still others like us
who are trying to get through Customs
at the San Francisco Airport,
but are being detained instead
because they are gay.
There's a man that could've prevented
these absurdities.
*This man had said that he would like to see
a kinder, gentler nation. *
*If you believe that the immigration policy
barring people living with HIV disease *
*from entering this country*
*is as useless as a health policy
and discriminatory as well,*
*please stand now and remain standing.*
♪ [music] ♪
[crowd shouting]
- *Join us in vocalizing our collective anger.*
*Join us in a chant against the man
who could bring down the INS barriers.*
*Join us in a chant against the man*
who has decided to show his commitment
to fighting AIDS by refusing to be here today.
Instead, he is at this very moment,
in North Carolina,
attending a fundraiser for the
homophobic author of the INS barriers,
*that pig in the Senate known as
Jesse Helms.*
[crowd shouting]
*Join us in this chant, *
Three hundred thousand dead from AIDS.
Where is George?!
[crowd chanting together]
Three hundred thousand dead from AIDS.
Where is George?!
- You can all now consider yourselves
members of ACT UP.
[applause]
- One of the things that happen
in San Francisco was that we found
we had won to move our NIH demands.
Fauci came up to me and said,
"We had a meeting, we decided that
we're gonna put you guys in all the committees
and we're gonna let your observers
go to the meetings
and the meetings won't be secret
anymore."
- Never again could any of these be done
without taking people with AIDS
and their advocates into consideration.
This would be public business from now on.
♪ [music] ♪
- *It was beginning to feel a little different
because we've spent all the time*
*being on the outside instead of
being on the door as we try to get in.*
*And now they actually wanted to hear
what we had to say. *
♪ [music] ♪
- We brought them in at Merck.
We made a very specific effort
to bring those individuals in
so that they would see what it is
that we were doing or trying to do
from the beginning.
- This was really fantastic stuff,
because we were sitting down with them
and sometimes with the very early stages
of development of a drug
and helping them plot out their strategy
toward designing clinical trials.
- The chemist who would work on the project,
the bunch--couple chemist said,
"Let's look at all these sporadic protease
inhibitors that we have on the shelf."
And they tested them and they found a few
molecules that actually worked.
The challenge to was, now you have these
molecules that were really good inhibitors
in your assay, which is just in a test tube.
When you put it into animals,
they just would never work or they would
never get absorbed by your system.
- And I remember being very disappointed
because I had to share this information,
instead of my own personal view which was,
this is gonna be a lot more difficult than
we thought that was gonna be originally
and in fact may not be possible,
*And Bill Bahlman said, *
*"Take a break, pick yourself up,
and go back at it." *
*If he and his colleagues and his friends
around the table can take that attitude*
*and do that, I remember saying to myself,*
"Emilio, you've got to right to say to yourself,
I don't know if I can do this."
And so off we went,
and we kept going at it.
- We're spending $4 billion a year on
AIDS research.
When you consider that
on a per capita basis
when you compare it to heart disease
or cancer, it's an awful lot.
- *[Newsman] Almost nothing stops
George Bush from a round of golf. *
*He's played nearly every day
and sometimes twice a day *
*during his August vacation. *
♪ [music] ♪
- *[George Bush] If the message is research,
I would say, "Please talk to Dr. Fauci"*
*and others at National Institute of Health"*
*Who would tell you that we're doing
pretty well in funding the research.*
♪ [music] ♪
[crowd shouting]
- *[Sen. Helms] The sensitivity of those
of us who feel that there is a spiritual*
*and moral aspect to this playing
to the homosexual lesbian crowd. *
*It makes it different from anything else. *
*I wish they shut their mouth and go to work,
*
*and keep their private matters to themselves*
and get their mentality out of their crotches.
- I'm here today because Jesse Helms
is the devil.
*Jesse Helms has worked for years
doing as much as he possibly can*
*to ensure the continuation
of the AIDS epidemic. *
- *The disease is spreading because
of him. *
And people are dying because of him.
- *This is an educational effort.
It's not a violation of people's property right. *
*We've been very careful that--
absolutely no damage is done. *
If any damage is done, whatever it is,
we will be happy to pay for it.
We have the money with us to pay for it.
- You guys don't wanna tangle with these people
because you don't wanna get AIDS,
I know, but what's next?
Come on, get out!
-*[Sen. Helms] If they will keep their mouth shut*
*and go about their business
with whatever their sexual orientation is,*
*nobody would ever say a word,
we would not even think about them. *
*But now they're marching the streets,
and they defy you to say anything about them.*
*Well they don’t like me
and I don’t like them. *
A bunch of them climbed up on my house
in Arlington
*and hoisted about a 35-foot canvas of condom
one day and protested a week.*
♪ [music] ♪
- Senator, when we started this,
I thought I was on your side,
particularly on the first amendment.
And on the first amendment,
people don't have to shut their mouths,
they have a right to speak.
- Well, they could speak just so long as
they don't offend anybody else, I suppose.
♪ [music] ♪
- Make sure your second coming
is a safe one.
Use condoms.
- *[Ray Navarro] Are you shooting? *
- *Yeah! I just turned it on.*
*Okay. Rolling. *
*Tell him we're rolling. *
- The machine is rolling.
You can start talking now, honey.
- Oh, I didn’t know she met now.
What I was gonna say was,
I love so much to go up to the 10th floor.
Because no one ever had explained to me
that there was going to be light again in the world
and that the whole world wasn’t going to be dark.
Some great challenges face us
as young people.
We're in our 20's and this is the challenge
that's been placed in front of me.
And who knows through camera,
*lots of other blind deaf men,
lived happy your lives. *
There are many years to come.
Let's hope.
So, what the hell,
life is worth living, isn't it?
♪ [music] ♪
- *[male voice] The death rates just kept on climbing.*
*We realized that science really
was up against a brick wall. *
*We kept getting new drugs approved
to prevent opportunistic infections *
*and then somebody would just get
another infection. *
- *So, Peter, where are we going?*
- We're gonna be going to the headquarters
of Daiichi Pharmaceutical Companies of Japan.
This is their U.S. Headquarters.
And we're blockading their offices because
they have a drug that's important
both to AIDS activists and the cancer activist,
specifically breast cancer.
That they've been dragging their feet on
for over two years now,
and we don't understand why,
but we certainly are gonna try
to let them understand why we're concerned.
- And everybody--
- *...see you again.*
- Yeah, just wait outside the elevators.
- *Shhhh! *
- *[Peter] Hi! We're with the ACT UP and we're doing
an ACT UP videos.* __
*Please remain calm. *
- *I'm here with Peter Ryan... *
- *We're from ACT UP New York. *
$ - We're here basically to demand
that you start to develop this drug $
$ as a potentially life-saving therapy $$
$$ for people with breast cancer
and Kaposi sarcoma. $$
- You already have the blood of
several-thousand people on your hands
and those of us like me
who have Kaposi sarcoma are gonna die,
and we are here until we get arrested.
- You seem to know nothing about the actual
details of the development of this drug.
Maybe you're just not telling us.
- *Mr. Borsick, can you schedule a meeting
with the FDA?*
- Yeah, as soon as we can.
- *[Peter] We have helped many companies
through this process. *
*We can take a drug from your test tube
to the market *
*in under two years if you work with us.*
*And we will pave the way for you
at the Food and Drug Administration. *
But if there's a total reluctance on your part,
it's gonna get you nowhere.
You'll end up killing us, alright?
- See this dark mark on my forehead?
That's Kaposi sarcoma.
It's gonna spread. It's gonna kill me.
You're coming to my funeral because
you're the man fucking responsible.
You are my murderer in your shirt and tie.
- *[Ed Bradley] Do you think that you'll live
to see a cure? *
- No, I don't.
- *[Ed] Do you think that you'll live? *
- No.
- You expect to die from this?
♪ [music] ♪
- *The anger just mounted
and mounted and mounted,*
*the more people who were dying.*
*Once a week we met,*
*and at that meeting, a lot of people came
who were just terrified *
*they weren’t gonna be alive
even the next week. *
*What can we do?
How can we get there?*
- *[Jim] I think ACT UPs anger turned in*
*after having been directed out so long. *
- *In it's first few years,
Treatment and Data pretty much *
*got everything it wanted
from the floor of ACT UP. *
*But as Treatment and Data was becoming
more and more technical, *
*there were a lot of people in the
general membership of ACT UP *
They saw that as an elite and that
maybe it would be better if
that elite was pulled in a bit.
- There was a fear I think that we were
getting too close to the people in power.
That we would compromise our own principles
and the people who were more interested
in the social issues became
uncomfortable with that.
- I remember this very decisive moment where
there was a proposal for moratorium
on meeting with drug companies
for six months.
And there was a huge and impassioned
debate over and someone said,
a woman, who is not HIV-positive said,
"Well, it's not like it's the rest of your life."
And for a lot of people in the room,
it was the rest of their lives.
[crowd chanting]
- *There were inevitable splits in priorities. *
- You know it quite well.
- *[male voice] I know. *
- And it was completely left out of the
NIH research agenda.
- *[male voice] I agree. *
- *I remember a lot of dirty tricks
that happened and a lot of fear*
*within the organization that various
factions had done this to each other.*
- Mark Harrington. Mark Harrington.
There's a video camera in here now.
Would you like to take an oath
that you will not write nasty
anonymous letters to people?
- I've been getting some
hate letters too, but those are unsigned.
I don't ever-- I don't ever--
- *So you keep on writing nasty letters to people?*
- There were a lot of charges
in the midst of that of sabotage and threats.
- [David Barr] Our last speaker is Larry Kramer.
- *[male voice] Why don’t you answer
the charges? *
- *[David] Bill, you're gonna have
the chance to speak, alright? *
*Everybody will get a chance to talk.*
- *[Bill] Don't lecture me*
*you stupid, lazy, incompetent shit ass.*
- *[David] Bill, everybody got the flyer--*
- *[Bill] You can't just lick his ass before he talks!*
- *[male voice] Shut the fuck up
and let him answer. *
- Look! There are a lot of people in the audience,
who wanna ask and talk about treatment.
And I think it's important that
you allow that to happen.
-*[Bill] Oh, are you gonna take away
free speech now?*
- [male voice] You're the one who's interfering
a speech right now. I don't--
[male shouting]
- *[male voice] You're making the same point
George Bush -- *
- PLAGUE! We are in the middle of a
fucking plague!
and you behave like this!
PLAGUE!
Forty million infected people
is a fucking plague!
We are in the worst shape
we have ever, ever, ever been in!
All those pills we're shoveling down
our throats! Forget it!
ACT UP has been taken over by a lunatic fringe
that can't get together!
Nobody agrees with anything!
All we can do is field a couple of hundred
people at a demonstration!
That's not gonna make anybody
pay attention!
Not until we get millions out there!
We can't do that!
All we do is pick at each other,
and yell at each other!
And I say to you, in year 10,
the same thing I said to you in 1981
when there were 41 cases.
Until we get our acts together,
all of us--we are as good as dead.
- *In the end,
the Treatment and Data guys,*
*Peter, Garance, Mark
and some others split off*
*and formed their own
separate organization. *
- *TAG was one of the little
mercury balls that flew off*
the main body of ACT UP, a more
think tank-typed project came about.
- *Mr. Harrington, a TAG member,
educated at the Harvard College. *
*And he has worked for a long time
on experimental treatments*
*for the disease
and also the basic science*
and Mr. Gonsalvez was born
in Long Island
and attended Tufts University,
also a TAG member.
I guess I can do nothing better than to
turn this conference over to my speakers.
- *I noticed that you're both sitting
up there in suits and ties. *
*Do you feel that your approach
is better than circling*
*NIH buildings and so forth?*
- I think that we like to keep our options
open, but it's silly to risk arrest
and the hassles that are tended upon
and if you can get serious attention
and negotiations going
with other measures.
- We've just released a report,
a critique of all the NIH's AIDS programs.
- The research is spread out over
12 agencies. There's no coordination.
There's a lot of duplications.
There's no leadership.
- The budget is shrinking and shrinking
as cases mount
and the President needs to be blamed
as well as the Congress.
Who cut the entire NIH budget
by 150 million two weeks ago.
- Our recommendations, I think,
are gonna require some legislation
and so we have to go to our friends on the hill
and see what wonders they could work for us.
♪ [music] ♪
- We had this one particular compound that
looked like it may have had the potency
and the physical properties that we wanted,
and it could be a possible drug.
- He said, "You know, let's put this in
HIV-infected individuals
and let's see what happens".
*So we went into a HIV-infected individuals
with this drug called Crixivan. *
*And you could see a very substantial drug. *
*Just with one protease inhibitor, you could
see very substantial drop in virus load. *
So that was the first week.
The second week was very disappointing.
Because what we saw
in the second week was in fact,
virus load coming right back up again.
One exception...
- There was one patient that--
patient #143, I believe, was his number,
that the virus went down
and stayed down.
- That told us that it was possible.
If it can happen in one, then by definition,
it can happen in everyone.
You just need to figure out
how to do it.
That puts you in a completely different place,
and in a completely different state of mind.
So then the question became,
"Okay, now what do we need to do
in order to make it possible?"
[crowd making noise]
- *This is the beginning of the
primary season to elect the next president.*
*We want to send a message
to all of the candidates. *
We have not seen them
actively address the AIDS plague
and we thought it would be best
to send a message
by voting with our feet in the streets.
- [applause]
- *I wanna call for a massive march
on Washington,*
*the weekend the AIDS quilt
is gonna be there. *
*We have got to surround the White House
with people concerned about AIDS *
to push Bush out of the White House!
- *[newsman] Last night,
a man with AIDS heckled Clinton, *
*charging that he had a bad record
on fighting AIDS in Arkansas. *
- When voter, Bob Rafsky met Bill Clinton,
it was anything but pleasant.
- [Robert] We're dying of AIDS.
What are you going to do about AIDS?
[applause]
- *[Bill Clinton] First of all,*
it will become a part of my obsession
as President.
- Bill, we're dying of neglect.
- That's why I'm running for president
to do something about this.
[Robert shouting]
- Would you just calm down?
I feel your pain!
But if you wanna attack me personally,
you're no better than Jerry Brown
and all the rest of these people who say
whatever sounds good at the moment.
If you want something to be done,
you ask me a question and you listen.
If you don’t agree with me,
go support somebody else for president,
but quit talking to me like that.
This is not a matter of personal attack,
it's a matter of human wrong.
[applause]
- I came here tonight
because I'm dying from AIDS.
And it doesn’t matter to me
who the next president is,
if they don’t change 11 years of
government neglect of this epidemic.
- *Okay, first off. *
What happened this week was AIDS
became an issue in this campaign.
[applause]
*I'd like to call down *
Bob Rafsky.
[applause]
♪ [music] ♪
[crowd shouting]
- Never debate a world scholar,
it gets you into a world of trouble.
It looks like what we have to do
is to keep forcing these clowns
to say the right things so that if one
of them happens to become president,
we can hold them accountable
for doing the right thing.
- *[male audience] Yeah! *
- But I just--it's always important to say
that we all know that the names of the people
who might save our lives are not
Bill Clinton, Jerry Brown, etc.
The names of the people who might save
our lives are Iris Long, Mark Harrington,
Peter Staley, etc. And they are the ones
who will be remembered
as the heroes of this epidemic, as well as
those who have gone before.
[applause]
- [Kid talking]
- Oh, I haven’t showered so I'm not--
- No, I'm just playing in--
- *This is Bob's birthday, July 22nd, 1992.*
- Are you ready?
Are you ready for the pyrotechnics?
- *[kid] Yeah! *
[applause]
- *Lydia De Rios. Steve H.
My friends, David Evans, Nicholas Kaiser,*
*George Marshall,
and my beloved brother, Dennis Jay. *
- *Robert R. Hackett,
Philip Gregory Alliston. *
*Teri Ronan. *
- *Michael Benetton. *
[voice unintelligible]
- *Tina Chao.
Perry Ellis. *
*Freddie Mercury.
Peter Allen. *
*To the thousand of other people
who were made to suffer in silence. *
[crowd shouting]
♪ [music] ♪
- *I think the group itself does
good stuff and it's moving, *
*still it's like making something beautiful
out of the epidemic *
*and I felt like doing something like this
is a way of showing, *
there's nothing beautiful about it.
You know, this is what I'm left with.
I've got a box full of ashes
and bone chips.
You know, there's new beauty in that.
And I felt like a statement like this
is like saying,
"This is what George Bush has done".
"This is what him and Ronald Reagan
before him have done."
*These are our love ones
and this is what they'd been reduced to*
*and we're bringing them to the person
who's responsible for their death. *
♪ [music] ♪
[crowd chanting]
[crowd chanting] BRING THE DEAD TO YOUR DOOR!
WE WON'T TAKE THIS ANYMORE!
♪ [music] ♪
[crowd chanting]
- *I love you Mike! *
- Welcome to the first of three debates
among the major candidates
for president of the United States,
*sponsored by the
Commission on Presidential Debates. *
- Mr. President, yesterday,
tens of thousands of people
paraded pass the White House to demonstrate
their concern about the disease AIDS.
A celebrated member of your Commission,
Magic Johnson,
quipped saying
that there was too much inaction.
*Where is this widespread feeling
coming from that your administration *
is not doing enough about AIDS?
I can't tell you where it's coming from,
but I am very much concerned about AIDS.
And I believe that we've got the
best researchers in the world
out there at NIH working the problem.
*It's one of the few disease
where behavior matters. *
And I once called on somebody, well,
change your behavior,
if the behavior, you're using prone to cause AIDS,
change the behavior.
The next thing I know, one of these
ACT UP group is out saying,
*"Bush ought to change his behav..."
You can't talk about it rationally. *
- *[Robert] Let everyone here know that this is not
a political funeral for Mark Fischer, *
*who wouldn’t let us burn or bury
his courage or his love for us*
*any more than he would like the earth
take his body, *
*until it was already in flight.*
- *He asked for this ceremony
not so we could bury him, *
*but so we could celebrate
his undying anger. *
*This isn't a political funeral
for Mark. *
It's a political funeral
for the man who killed him,
and so many others
and is slowly killing me,
whose name curls my tongue,
and curddles my breath,
George Bush, we believe
you'll be defeated tomorrow,
because we believe there's still
some justice left in the universe,
and some compassion left
in the American people.
For whether or not you are here now
standing by Mark's body,
we put this curse on you.
Mark's spirit will haunt you
until the end of your days,
so that in the moment of your defeat,
you'll remember our defeats.
And in the moment of your death,
you'll remember our deaths.
As for Mark, when the living can no
longer speak, the dead may speak for them.
*Mark's voice is here with us,
as is the voice of Pericles,*
who two millenniums ago, mourned
the Athenian soldiers who didn't have to die
and in whose death he was complicit.
But who had an ability to say
that their memorial was the whole earth.
Let the whole earth hear us now.
We beg, we pray, we demand!
That this epidemic end!
Not just so we may live, but so that
Mark's soul may rest in peace at last.
And in anger and in grief,
this fight is not over until all of us is safe.
ACT UP, fight back, fight AIDS.
♪ [music] ♪
- The debate over AIDS therapy
has re-ignited with a new European study
that challenges
the effectiveness of AZT, the widely
prescribed drug used to treat the HIV virus.
- *[Larry] This study just proves
what every other study proves *
is that the drug is at best modest,
mostly useless,
not good for you in the beginning.
- *[newsman] Two other drugs, DDI and DDC,
were approved because they were*
*as good as AZT, which means that
they might not be very useful either. *
*All this is profoundly dispiriting
for advocates of people with AIDS. *
- We thought we had made some advance
in AIDS treatment over the last five years
and these studies showed
that we really haven’t.
- *Many activists now admit,
their demands were short-sighted. *
- And it's been a huge expenditure,
a waste of money for the U.S. tax payer,
and it was naivete on our part to think
that the magic bullet was out there,
it just had to be tested in humans
and give it to us as the cure.
- Many doctors and scientists say
the bleak results presented here
indicate U.S. government needs
to substantially reorganize
the way it conducts AIDS research.
Robert Bazell, NBC News, Berlin.
- It's been this big crisis of St. Vincent's
about the way that we talked about
what happened in Berlin.
A couple of doctors said they were afraid
of people committing suicide now.
- I don't feel like, "Oh now, I wanna give up.
Now, I wanna stop living,
because AZT doesn’t work."
- I felt forever now that I'm not gonna
outlive this epidemic.
*That I will die from this. *
- You know maybe that is our future,
that we're gonna watch each other die.
That's not a new thought.
We've been thinking that ever since
we started the group.
- *The way of the recent spate of deaths--*
I don't know, it all seems
so much more apocalyptic.
Like the story doesn’t seem to have this
relationship to effective treatment
or a cure anymore.
It now seems to have
this relationship to death.
It is with everybody dying,
we're the last person alive in Chelsea,
please turn out the lights.
- Joining me now is Dr. David Kessler,
the commissioner of the
Food and Drug administration.
Dr. Kessler, how excited should we get
about this new family of drugs,
these protease inhibitors?
- I don't wanna over-promise,
but these are the most potent drugs
we've seen against the virus.
- I know that you are pushing
for faster FDA approval of these drugs,
I know that the application has just gone
for the first of these drugs to the FDA,
it's still gonna take six months.
- We will turn around that application
as quick as ever.
We are proving drugs
in a matter of months these days.
- But you were telling me, that's six months,
right? That's as quick as possible.
- We may be able to do it
even a little quicker.
- *[newsman] A split has developed between
those who want rapid approval *
*based on early indicators of success,
and the Treatment Action Group, or TAG.*
*TAG has asked the FDA to reconsider
the accelerated approval process. *
- *[Peter] We we told the FDA,*
*"No, the company has asked you
to approve that drug too soon.*
*They need a little bit more data first.*
- *[newsman] TAG is asking the FDA
to take a closer look at Saquinavir, *
*the first protease inhibitor
to seek approval. *
- *We need to make sure we don't repeat
the mistake we made with AZT and DDI.*
*This is a new class of drugs.
We need to know if it works. *
- *The battle over early approval
of Saquinavir was a really pivotal moment*
*for treatment activism and we took
such shit for it from within.*
- There are a lot of people who do agree
that there are problems,
series of problems the way drug testing
and drug trials are run.
But there are many of us who feel that
halting--
accelerated approval is not necessarily
the answer.
- *[Bill] Tenet made their proposal
for this large simple trial *
of 18,000 people that they wanna put
in a placebo-controlled trial,
where one-third will get placebo.
They pushed this idea on the FDA
at a secret meeting,
which was not announced to the community.
*This is something we have fought
hard and long for. *
We've been arrested to get
accelerated approval through.
- It's the behavior that
I have a problem with.
It's the work they're doing
that I have a problem with,
and this is what I am gonna fight.
I'm not interested in mud wrestling with the boys.
I am absolutely enraged that there are people
who have appointed themselves
a elitist representatives, and represent
themselves as a single voice of this epidemic.
I am gonna fight them.
My patients are gonna fight them.
And you God damn will go fight them!
- Currently, there's this big discussion
on accelerated approval
and _ last week on the floor._
So we just wanted to give you
sort of the TAG perspective
and give you a sense of our proposal
around pre-AIDS drug development
so we can start from a baseline
common understanding and knowledge.
this proposal is not about taking
expanded access away,
taking accelerated approval away.
This is about adding something.
This is about figuring out how do we get
information about how to actually use these drugs.
We need more people when you have
a less powerful drug.
If we give them the penicillin
we could do it to 20 people.
So we put together a large
simple trial that tried to synthesize
expanded access in large simple trial.
And what we did is we presented it to Merck.
We presented it to the FDA.
We wanted to start a community discussion.
- I just wanted to thank Greg and Derek
for coming to tell us about this.
[applause]
- because we hadn’t heard anything
until we read about it in Barrons.
- If you wanted to hear the proposal
you could have heard it 40 times.
*It's been talked about all over. *
- *Dr. Conley wants to speak. *
- TAG is talking about getting
accurate information.
ACT UP is talking about making drug available.
There should be a way to mesh those two.
It's really not one or the other.
These two groups are really
talking pass one another.
Try not to scream, try not to go for
each other's throats.
But just talk, because the difference is
really can be breached.
[crowd shouting]
- *[David] Ninety-three to ninety-five
were the worst years. *
It was a really terrifying time.
They were the worst years.
And then we got lucky.
♪ [music] ♪
- And I just lose in it.
And just so many--
so many good people.
And...
You know...
like any war, you wonder why
you came home--
♪ [music] ♪
- *Mark collected all of our writings.
Pieces that all of us had done about *
what had gone wrong in the ways that
we studied the previous drugs
and what we were already doing wrong
in terms of trying to figure out
what do the protease inhibitors were.
*And we published to this big report
and started passing them out*
*everywhere we went.
Let's do the study. *
- They elevated themselves by their own
self education about these things.
And then it became very, very clear that
you weren’t gonna mess with these people
because they knew exactly
what you were talking
and they knew exactly
what they were talking about.
- Activists created a system that was able
to do everything faster, better, cheaper
more ethically and more effectively.
- *They forced people to put together
the right clinical trials *
*where you have the patient in mind
and you weren’t cut in corners. *
and of course the big breakthrough
was combination therapy.
because monotherapy was clearly
not the way to go.
- So let's go back into patients,
and let's go back into patients
with Crixivan plus AZT plus 3TC.
- The activist proposed a study design,
the industry used it,
it got the drug approved in six months.
- So I was at a meeting in Washington
and I stood up there
and I showed for the first time the data
in the study.
- *The data goes up on the screen
and everyone gasped and camera started to click *
and it's a realization that this is--
this is really great drug and it could work.
- I remember sitting there in a hotel room
in Washington D.C.
our hotel banquet room and just crying,
it was like, "We did it! We did something."
- It was too much to take it at that point.
It wasn’t until we started putting the drugs
in our bodies. And we all went home
and started--
went straight on that regimen
that had been on that slide,
including Crixivan and two nucleoside analogues.
And sure enough it happened in us
within 30 days.
All of us, undetectable, undetectable,
undetectable.
- The dying was stopping with
triple-drug combination.
*and if you need your clinical trial,
you could just go to these hospitals *
*that were not filling up the way
they were filling up with people with HIV.*
- You would see their Kaposi sarcoma lesions
that had been bright and red and big,
melting back into their skin.
- They were calling it, the Lazarus effect,
people who were deathly ill
get put on this drug and all of a sudden
they're working again,
that was a phenomenal feeling.
- It worked.
You know, we did something remarkable.
- So that breakthrough that we thought
was gonna happen in '88 or'89
if we just work fast enough.
You know, it did happen...
but not until '96 and so...
you know, a lot of people died,
maybe if Reagan had started putting money
into AIDS a little earlier...
[sniffling]
they wouldn’t all be dead.
- I feel very fortunate. And there's probably
a lot of complicated reasons why
but I still find it very difficult
to plan for the future and/or accept
that I will have long life, which is unfortunate
because I've had a long life
and I've been living with AIDS for 20 years.
But it's hard for me to relax into life.
- I know lots of us went through really
difficult times after--
trying to figure out what do I do now?
Not just because I didn’t think
I had a future, now I do,
so I have to make some plans.
But how do I do something else that is as--
I mean, it's a weird word but, as fulfilling
as that work has been.
- To be that threatened with extinction,
and to not lay down,
but instead to stand up and to fight back,
*The way we did it, the way we took care
of ourselves and each other, *
*the goodness that we showed,
the humanity that we showed the world *
*is just mind boggling, just incredible. *
[crowd chanting]
- *[Larry] Every single drug that's out there
is because of ACT UP, I am convinced. *
*We have the brain power
and we have the street power. *
*We have the good cops
and the bad cops.*
The government didn’t get us the drugs,
no one else got us the drugs.
WE, ACT UP, got those drugs out there.
It is the proudest achievement
that the gay population of this world
can ever claim.
- We could do it because
we could deliver hundred
and sometimes of thousands of bodies.
We had people with AIDS putting their bodies
on the line, flopping out in the streets
saying, "Fine. It's my body, take me away."
- I drew the line there, I didn’t wanna
get arrested [laughing].
That far, I wouldn’t go.
$$ The number of companies now
making effective protease inhibitors: 7 $$
$$ The number of lives saved:
6,000,000 $$
- *[Peter] I'd like to close with words written
by fellow AIDS activist, Peter Russo. *
*When the future generations ask
what we did in the war, *
*We have to be able to tell them
that we were out here fighting. *
And we have to leave a legacy
to the generations
of people who will come after us.
Remember that someday,
the AIDS crisis will be over.
And when that day has come and gone,
there will be a people alive on this earth,
gay people and straight people,
black people and white people,
men and women, who will hear the story,
that once, there was a terrible disease,
and that a brave group of people
stood up and fought,
and in some cases died, so that
others might live and be free.
♪ [music] ♪
$$ The number of people who die
because they can't afford AIDS drugs: $$
$$ 2,000,000 every year
5,000 every day, 4 every minute $$
$$ ACT UP END AIDS. $$
- [Peter talking]
- Ouch! That hurts!
- Our information is essential
so that doctors and patients
can make intelligent treatments.
- *Okay. *
- Alright.
- [male talking]
- No, I won't take that.
- I'm really glad to see everybody here.
You look really good.
- I'd like to suggest that we not be unethical
to do a randomized trial
on two different prevention programs.
- If we don't eradicate HIV everywhere
we will never eradicate it anywhere.
- We may march without incident
or they may arrest us,
but it'll all be fun.
- [male talking]
- We're going to end it today.
♪ [music] ♪
- In just over two years, that drug
went from test tube to full approval.
[applause]
♪ [music] ♪